Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim,
and this is Geshe Michael Roach.
The picture you just saw
is Master Dharmakirti.
He lived about 1,500 years ago.
He is going to help us prove something.
He is a great debater. He
is a great logistician.
He is the master of clear thinking.
Nowadays, I don't like to call it logic.
Everybody hates logic. Logic is boring.
But Master Dharmakirti, he was like,
"Clear thinking. Clear thinking.
Just learn clear thinking.
If you see smoke, there must be fire."
How can we use that to
develop bodhichitta?
We are going to try to develop
a vision of the bodhisattvas.
But to do this method, we
are going to have to prove
that everyone has been our mom.
Let's go to the text. It is called...
He quotes, Pabongka
Rinpoche, in his Lam Rim,
he quotes a verse by Dharmakirti,
or he starts quoting him and he says,
,SKYE BA YONGS SU LEN PA NA,
,'BYUNG RNGUB DBANG PO BLO DAG NI,
,RANG GI RIGS LA LTOS MED CAN
SKYE BA YONGS SU LEN PA NA means
when you take your rebirth,
BYUNG RNGUB, 'BYUNG means to breathe in,
and RNGUB means to breathe out.
When you do basic meditation
practice of breathing,
watching your breath,
watching ten breaths,
before you meditate to focus your mind,
in the Abhidharma Kosha
this is called DBUGS 'BYUNG RNGUB.
So 'BYUNG RNGUB means exhale and inhale.
DBANG PO means the sense
powers that you are born with:
your eyes, ears, nose,
tongue and your skin.
BLO DAG NI - and your mind.
RANG GI RIGS LA LTOS MED CAN
They are not something
which depends on something
of their own type.
Your breathing, the clarity
of your senses and your mind
are not something which depends
on the same type of thing.
Then he cuts the quotation
from Dharmakirti.
I thought, this is a great quotation,
this is a great teaching.
It is an entire teaching.
And he mentions it, but
he doesn't teach it.
So I thought, why don't we go
learn this particular verse
from Master Dharmakirti,
which is incredibly important
and incredibly beautiful.
I had the honor, 25 years ago
at the monastery, to help a great scholar.
He is the teacher of my
main scripture teacher.
My main scripture teacher
is Geshe Thubten Rinchen
from Sera Mey. A great,
great, great scholar,
a great teacher, extraordinary
teacher, who has taught
many, many, many geshes.
His teacher was Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk,
who did not come out of Tibet
during the cultural
revolution. He stayed in Tibet.
So we did not know what
was happening with him.
But later he was able
to visit the monastery,
and he said, "By the way, I
have a book for you guys."
And we're like, "What?"
And he said, "It is
just something I wrote."
And it's like, in English
it would be like 8,000 pages
that he had written about Dharmakirti,
about this great, great
debater from 1,500 years ago.
We looked at it. My
teachers and I looked at it,
and it was unbelievable.
He explains Dharmakirti's greatest book,
word by word, and I have never
seen anyone who did that.
So then, usually if a book is modern,
if it is not a thousand years
old, we kind of look at it,
in the monastery, and we are like,
It's okay, that's nice.
But as we checked his book,
we realized it is a great classic.
It will stay for a
thousand years, I think.
It is a great, great classic.
I actually was allowed to
join the team, his team,
and we produced two volumes.
It was in two large volumes.
We typed in the whole text.
He checked the whole text.
My responsibility was to put in
the root text of Dharmakirti
at the right places.
So, this book means a lot to me,
and it is a great, great commentary.
Let's go see what Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk,
one of the greatest explainers
of Master Dharmakirti, says
about recognizing people as your mom.
Don't forget that is what
we are trying to prove:
have people been your mom or not?
So here are the full verses:
,SKYE BA YONGS SU LEN PA NA,
,'BYUNG RNGUB DBANG PO BLO DAG NI,
,RANG GI RIGS LA LTOS MED CAN,
,LUS NYID 'BA ZHIG LAS SKYE MIN,
I am not going to,
I am just going to read it roughly,
and then, we won't understand
everything, and then
we are going to go into Geshe
Yeshe Wangchuk's commentary,
and he is going to make everything clear.
The goal is, by the end of this class,
which is going to be a
little bit long, okay?
Don't worry.
We are going to try to prove that
the people around you have been your mom.
That is a great proof, and
that is one of the greatest
classical reasons for logic
is to prove your past and future lives,
and to prove that everyone
has been your mother.
Why do Buddhists study reasoning or logic?
It is to prove things like
everyone has been your mom,
and then you are going to
treat people differently,
if you realize, if you
can prove to yourself
that they have been your mom.
Then you are halfway on the
way to be a bodhisattva.
SKYE BA YONGS SU LEN PA NA
means when you take a rebirth.
BYUNG RNGUB DBANG PO BLO DAG NI
The breathing in and out,
the clarity of your sense
powers, your awareness.
RANG GI RIGS LA LTOS MED CAN
Something which does not depend
on something that came before them.
MIN, next line,
they are not something
which does not depend
on what came before them. Unfortunately,
Pabongka Rinpoche leaves
out that word, purposely.
LUS NYID 'BA ZHIG LAS SKYE MIN
They do not just come from your body.
We are going to get the explanation later.
,HA CANG THAL PHYIR MTSAMS SBYOR BAR,
,NUS LDAN MTHONG BA GANG DE LA,
,CI ZHIG YOD 'GYUR GANG MED PA,
,GANG GIS PHYI NAS MTSAMS SBYOR MED,
HA CANG THAL PHYIR
means it is too much,
logically, it is too much.
MTSAMS SBYOR BAR
When you make the crossing to a new life.
NUS LDAN MTHONG BA GANG DE LA
You see that your senses
have their own powers.
CI ZHIG YOD 'GYUR GANG MED PA
You check what is there. Nothing is there.
,GANG GIS PHYI NAS MTSAMS SBYOR MED,
What was it that made the crossing
into your new life from your old life?
,GANG DU DROD GSHER LA SOGS PA,
,SKYE BO SKYE BAR MI 'GYUR BA'I,
,SA SOGS CHA DE 'GA' YANG MED,
,DE PHYIR THAMS CAD SA BON BDAG,
GANG DU DROD GSHER LA SOGS PA
Let us take cases where beings appeared
to be growing from warmth and
liquid and wet and moisture.
SKYE BO SKYE BAR MI 'GYUR BA'I
If they are not born that way,
GSA SOGS CHA DE 'GA' YANG MED
then they don't have any
parts of the element of earth.
DE PHYIR THAMS CAD SA BON BDAG
Therefore, everything consists of seeds.
It does not make sense yet, don't worry,
I just want to get the
root text in your mind.
,DE PHYIR DBANG SOGS RANG RIGS LA,
,LTOS PA MED PAR 'BYUNG YIN NA,
,JI LTAR GCIG NI YONGS 'GYUR BZHIN,
,KUN 'GYUR KHYAD PAR MED PHYIR RO,
DE PHYIR DBANG SOGS RANG RIGS LA
If the sense powers
don't depend on their own
type of thing before,
'BYUNG YIN NA, JI LTAR
GCIG NI YONGS 'GYUR BZHIN
in the way that one happened,
KUN 'GYUR KHYAD PAR MED PHYIR RO
Everything would happen the same way.
,DBANG RNAMS RE RE LA GNOD NA,
,YID BLO LA GNOD YOD MA YIN,
,'DI 'GYUR NA NI DE DAG KYANG,
,'GYUR BA BDAG TU MTHONG BA YIN,
DBANG RNAMS RE RE LA GNOD NA
If we heard the idea that there
could be each sense power,
YID BLO LA GNOD YOD MA YIN
it is not necessarily hurting
the sense of the thoughts.
'DI 'GYUR NA NI DE DAG KYANG
If it were that way,
'GYUR BA BDAG TU MTHONG BA YIN
you would see them changing as well.
Do not worry about the meaning,
I am just loading them words in your mind.
,DE PHYIR BLO GNAS PA YIN RTEN,
,BLO NYID LA NI BRTEN PA 'GA',
,DBANG PO RNAMS KYI RGYU YIN PAS,
,DE PHYIR BLO LAS DBANG PO YIN,
DE PHYIR BLO GNAS PA YIN RTEN
Therefore, the staying
of the mind is the basis.
BLO NYID LA NI BRTEN PA 'GA'
What is it that rests upon the mind?
DBANG PO RNAMS KYI RGYU YIN PAS
If the sense powers are the cause,
DE PHYIR BLO LAS DBANG PO YIN
therefore, the mind is
coming from the sense powers.
DE 'DRA'I 'PHEN BYED YOD GYUR NA,
PHYIS KYANG DE 'DRAR 'GYUR BA YIN,
If the karma that throws these things
into existence is like that,
then later it should be the same.
That is all, that is all
the Dharmakirti says,
and it is completely un-understandable.
You cannot understand it.
Now, here comes Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk,
he is walking into room
and says, "Don't worry, I am your man,
I will explain this to you.
In fact, I will give you an explanation,
and in every sentence I will
use Dharmakirti's own words."
That is called a @ZHING 'DREL.
I will put Dharmakirti's
words inside the sentence,
and we'll prove that everyone
has been your mother.
Wow, okay, let's do it.
BYIS PA SKYE MA THAG
PA'I DBUGS 'BYUNG RNGUB
Now, comes the commentary.
BYIS PA SKYE MA THAG
PA'I DBUGS 'BYUNG RNGUB
means look, when children are first born,
they start breathing.
I am thinking of Maitri, which is the son
of two of our friends,
Noor and Seiji Arao.
They just had a child. Here
is the baby, beautiful baby,
and it came out two months
ago, and six weeks ago,
and he started breathing.
DBANG PO DVANGS PA,
means his sense powers,
his eyes are alive.
You can look at his eyes
and you know he is already,
maybe he does not see clearly,
but he is already looking at things/
BLO'I G-YER BAG SOGS CHOS CAN,
G-YER BAG here means the
tendency, mental tendency.
You can say his mood, the child's mood.
The child has specific moods.
When a kid comes out of their mom,
already, within a few
days, they are breathing,
they have powers, they are looking around,
and mind in the root
text means G-YER BAG CAN.
They have an attitude.
Some kids are cranky.
Some kids are generous.
Some kids are happy.
I know Veronica had two boys.
She said one boy was happy all the time.
One boy was crying all the time.
They were not different.
They did not grow up in a different house.
They didn't grow up with different food.
They just had this, what do you call it?
This kind of nature or
attitude about them.
What is the other word for that?
[Student] Personality?
Personality, different personalities.
That is called G-YER BAG CAN.
They have different
personalities, from the beginning.
So then, he says, these things:
the life in the being, the
breathing which indicates life,
the sensory awareness and the personality,
which is the mind, right?
SKYE BA YONGS SU LEN
PA NA RANG GI RIGS 'DRA
Now, I am going to follow the root text.
I have underlined the root text,
so you can see how Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk
mixed the root text into his
sentence, very beautiful.
He did not make any miss any words.
SKYE BA YONGS SU LEN PA NA
When that child takes birth,
RANG GI RIGS 'DRA SNGA MA
LA BLTOS MED CAN MA YIN
those beautiful eyes,
that life expressed in
breathing, and that personality
that he is already
showing, and by the way,
Maitri is kind of very happy, friendly,
his main personality is hungry.
Like Geshe Michael, no.
But these are not something
which came out of nowhere:
his breathing, his life, and
his bright eyes looking around,
and his own smile, happy personality,
they must be like smoke and fire.
They must be like smoke and fire.
His personality, the
brightness of his eyes,
and the fact that he is
alive are like smoke.
They are signs of something
that happened before.
When you see smoke, you see fire.
When you see awareness,
it must have come from something similar.
That's all, that's all where we are at.
Maitri's eyes are like smoke,
something that happened
before he came out and
his mom, is like fire.
We cannot see the fire. That
was all happening inside.
But we can see the smoke.
So can we make some
conclusions from the smoke?
That is all.
DBUGS 'BYUNG RNGUB DANG,
DBANG PO DVANGS PA, BLO'I G-YER
BAG SOGS DANG LDAN PA'I PHYIR
He is breathing, he has
bright sense powers,
and his mind has a certain
kind of personality.
'BYUNG BA'I LUS NYID 'BA'
ZHIG LAS SKYE BA MIN TE
Did the brightness of Maitri's eyes
and the life expressed in his breathing,
and his personality, did
they only come from his skin?
Did those three things come from his skin?
Is that where they came from?
His personality came from his skin?
And his bright eyes and
awareness of the world
came from his skin?
And his breathing, his
life itself, does it?
Is it some result of his skin?
When you look at his
eyes, and his personality,
and his awareness, like smoke,
and you try to guess what was the fire,
is the cause of those
three things his skin?
Only his skin, you see?
'BYUNG BA'I LUS NYID 'BA'
ZHIG LAS SKYE BA MIN TE
No, Dharmakirti says, Geshe
Yeshe Wangchuk says no.
RIGS 'DRA SNGA MA LAS SKYES PA'I PHYIR
Things are always coming from
other things of the same type.
Things always come from other
things of the same type.
You do not get awareness from skin.
You get awareness from awareness.
You get personality from
the personality before.
You get sense awareness
from sense awareness.
RANG GI RIGS CAN
means when you are looking for the cause
of something, you look
for something similar.
Awareness should come from awareness.
Sensation should come from sensation.
Personality should come from personality.
Not that they all come from
your skin. That's Dharmakirti.
RIGS 'DRA SNGA MA LAS SKYES PA'I PHYIR,
DE LTA MIN NA HA CANG THAL
If you say all that
stuff came from his skin,
that is all, come on, that is BS.
HA CANG THAL means too much, too much.
Who said that?
Dharmakirti.
HA CANG THAL BA means
come on. Get real, man.
It means get real, man.
Come on. Get real. What
really happened here?
'BYUNG BA KUN SROG CHAGS SU THAL
Then all the skin in the world,
and all the chemicals in the skin:
the carbon, and the
oxygen, and the nitrogen,
they must all be babies. There
must be babies everywhere.
Everywhere there is oxygen,
everywhere there is carbon,
everywhere there is nitrogen,
Poof! Oh, there is another Maitri.
Does it come from your skin?
Does it come from the chemicals?
Yes, you can show the chemicals.
Does it come from your chemicals?
Does Maitri's awareness
and Maitri's friendliness,
does it come from chemicals?
Okay, you are right.
Then, anytime you have that
chemical, you have a smile.
Right?
That must be.
Why do the chemicals
sometimes make a smile
and why the same chemical
does not make a smile?
YIN PAR THAL
YID BLO 'BYUNG BA 'BA'
ZHIG LAS SKYE BA'I PHYIR
Because according to you,
YID BLO means the mind,
that awareness of the child,
comes from the 'BYUNG BA.
Here 'BYUNG BA means the four elements:
SA CHU ME RLUNG
earth, water, fire, and wind,
which is the Tibetan way
of saying chemicals: carbon,
nitrogen, oxygen, etcetera.
Then, everywhere you have chemicals
you must have Maitri popping out.
Why?
Because Maitri just came from chemicals.
His personality came from chemicals.
All kids must be as friendly as Maitri
because all kids have carbon.
YIN PAR THAL
SKYES MA THAG PA'I RIG PA
RANG GI RIGS 'DRA SNGA MA LAS
PHYI MA MTSAMS SBYOR BAR NUS
PA DANG LDAN PA MTHONG BA DE LA
SKYES MA THAG PA'I RIG PA
When you look at the
awareness of the child
who is just born,
RANG GI RIGS 'DRA SNGA MA LAS
PHYI MAMTSAMS SBYOR BAR NUS PA
There must have been some ability
in the cause of Maitri's friendliness
that created Maitri's friendliness, right?
When Maitri was friendly,
after he came out of his mom, Noor,
then, there must have been
some friendliness before that.
NUS PA DANG LDAN PA MTHONG BA DE LA
You can see that.
RGYU LHAG PO CI ZHIG KYANG
YOD PAR GYUR PA MI DGOS PA
GANG GI PHYIR NA, PHYI NAS KYANG
RIG PA PHYI MAR MTSAMS
SBYOR BA MED PA MA YIN NO
It is not the case that
Maitri died five minutes
after he was born. The
mind that was friendly,
just after he came out,
continues to be friendly.
The friendly mind of Maitri
when he is three years old
is a sign that Maitri had a friendly mind
when he was one year old.
And that is a sign of something before.
When you see a kid who
is friendly by nature,
G-YER BAG CAN, personality,
at three years old,
then you can think there
must have been some seeds
for that in his mind
when he was one year old.
But who put the seeds in his
mind when he was one year old.
You have to think it came
from something similar.
GANG DU DROD GSHER LAS SKYES
PA LA SOGS PA SKYE BO SKYE BAR
MI'GYUR BA'I SA SOGS 'BYUNG BA'I
CHA DE 'GA' YANG MED PA DE'I PHYIR
According to you, then,
every time you see,
'BYUNG BA'I DE
CHA DE 'GA' YANG MED PA DE'I PHYIR,
'BYUNG BA THAMS CAD SROG CHAGS KYI
SA BON GYI BDAG NYID CAN DU 'GYUR RO,
Then of course, any time there is life,
anytime there are chemicals, then,
then that should produce
Maitri's friendliness.
If Maitri's friendliness is
just coming from his skin,
or the chemicals in his body,
and if that is the cause
that turned into his friendliness,
in the way that his
one-year-old friendliness
turned into his
three-year-old friendliness,
then it must be that chemicals
can produce friendliness,
and that means you can make friendliness
in a laboratory with the
right chemicals, right?
I guess the bottles of chemicals
will be friendly or something.
DE LTAR NA HA CANG THAL BA'O
And that is a little bit too much,
excuse me, HA CANG THAL BA'O.
Come on, that is too much.
DBANG PO RNAMS RE RE LA GNOD PA YOD NA'ANG
YID BLO RTOG PA LA GNOD
PA YOD PAS MA KHYAB LA
YID BLO RTOG PA LA MYA NGAN
SOGS KYIS KYIS GNOD NAS
'GYUR NA DBANG PO DE DAG
KYANG 'GYUR BA DAG TU
MTHONG BA YIN PA'I PHYIR
What is the relationship
between the sense powers
and Maitri's state of mind?
What is the relationship
between his physical eye,
his physical ear, his physical nose,
and how he is feeling, his personality?
What is the relationship between his nose
and his personality?
DBANG PO RNAMS RE RE LA GNOD PA YOD NA'ANG
Look, you can hurt the nose
and the mind can stay friendly.
It is possible. I had a
friend, we saw her last night,
Kayla, her daughter. Did you know?
Her daughter was bitten badly by a dog,
and part of her nose was cut very badly.
But the child is very sweet.
It means, if Maitri's skin was creating
Maitri's personality, then
when you cut the skin,
Maitri's personality should
get mean. But it does not.
That indicates that maybe the skin
is not the cause of Maitri's
personality. Got it?
You can hurt the skin,
but you do not necessarily
change the personality. But,
YID BLO RTOG PA LA MYA NGAN
SOGS KYIS GNOD NAS 'GYUR NA
But if you hurt the mind,
it tends to hurt the body.
If a person's depressed for a long period,
usually their health will suffer,
usually their physical
health will get worse.
So it is not the case
that the physical body
determines the state of the mind,
but it seems that the state of the mind
can affect the health
of the physical body.
Like that, he wants to go to this way.
MTHONG BA YIN PA'I PHYIR,
YID BLO RTOG PA DE'I RTEN
KHYAD PAR CAN GANG ZHIG NA,
RANG GI RIGS MTHUN BLO
SNGA MA NYID LA BRTEN PA'I
SNGON GYI SEMS PA'I LAS 'GA'
ZHIG DA LTAR YID BLO GNAS PA'I
RTEN YIN PA DE'I PHYIR,
YID BLO RTOG PA RTEN MED PA MA YIN NO,
So is it the case that
Maitri's personality
is without a basis?
In Buddhism, we say...
This is called BRTEN.
this is called RTEN.
And the handkerchief
is holding up the cup.
So this is called the
basis, the foundation.
And this is called what is
resting on the foundation.
This is Maitri's current
personality, that he is friendly.
It must be resting on
something in the past.
Something about his mind in the past
made his current mind friendly,
and this past state of mind
is holding up his current state of mind.
This is current Maitri's friendliness
is resting on something
in the past. It has to be.
All results are resting
on causes in the past.
We call it dependent origination.
This is current state of mind is resting
on some state of mind in the past.
RTEN YIN PA DE'I PHYIR,
YID BLO RTOG PA RTEN MED PA MA YIN NO
Therefore, it is not the case
that Maitri's personality
came out of no place, came from nowhere.
It is not the case that
one of Veronica's children
was crying all the time and
the other child was happy
all the time. It is not the
case that there is no cause
for that. There must be a cause for that.
It must have happened before they came out
because it came out that way.
The cause must be, the fire
must be under the smoke.
We can see the smoke,
which is the personality
of the newborn child, but
we can not see the fire,
but we can make some
assumptions about the fire.
We can try to use our logic to say,
there must have been something
before they came out.
I think I have a picture here.
This is silverware, I don'y know,
my mind is on tables and silverware,
because I am trying to get a cafe open.
Look, can you see the table,
which is holding up the dishes,
and the silverware and the glasses?
Can you see the table?
Yes or no?
The wooden table? You can not see.
You can see something is
holding up the glasses,
and the dishes and the silverware,
but it is covered with a cloth, right?
And you can not see it. That
cloth is the moment of birth.
The silverware and the dishes
is Maitri's friendly nature.
And Buddhism says, there must
be something behind the cloth.
If you look into the
darkness of the few hours
before Maitri was born,
is there something there?
Or before he was conceived?
Is there something there upon which
his friendliness is resting?
And shouldn't it be of the same type?
Being angry does not make
you friendly an hour later.
Being an angry person does not make you
a friendly person the next
year. Being a friendly person
makes you a friendly person the next year.
YID BLO LAS DBANG PO
RNAMS 'BYUNG BA YIN TE
That sense powers have come from the mind,
YID BLO SNGA MA 'GA'
ZHIG DBANG PO RNAMS KYI
'PHEN BYED KYI RGYU YIN PA DE'I PHYIR,
because according to Buddhism,
it was your consciousness
of your past life,
affected by mental
seeds, that has projected
your sense powers, your eyes, your ears,
your nose, into this life.
Maitri's friendliness did
not come from his skin.
His skin came from his friendliness.
Now Dharmakirti is like turning it around.
Again, I told you Maitri's state of mind
did not come from skin,
from his chemicals.
Okay, I got that. But you know what?
His chemicals did come from
his state of mind. Why?
Because they came from
the karma in his mind.
PHYIS 'CHI KHA'I SEMS SOGS
KYANG SNGA MA DANG 'DRA BAR
RIGS 'DRA PHYI MA MTSAMS
SBYOR BA 'GYUR BA YIN TE
According to the state
of the mind as you die,
strongly affects the state of
the mind when you come out.
RIGS 'DRA DE 'DRA'I 'PHEN BYED KYI
RGYU YOD PAR GYUR PA'I PHYIR
There must be a cause
similar to friendliness
that existed in the mind in the past.
RTZA 'GREL DE DAG NI
I think, I can say, we
have finished Dharmakirti.
We finished covering his verses.
Basically, what he is trying to say is
Maitri did not get his
friendliness from chemicals.
In fact, it seems to be proof,
there seems like there could
be some proof that his physical
body came from his karma,
from his mind.
And now, Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk begins
to interpret Dharmakirti for us.
That is what is so cool
about Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk.
First, he tells you the
meaning of the words.
Then, he stops and he says, "Now, okay,
we covered the words. Now you
know what the verses mean.
But what does it mean for us?"
That is Geshe Yeshe
Wangchuk. That is his style.
What does it mean for us?
Then he says, RTZA 'GREL DE
DAG NI, SKYE BA SNGA PHYI
YOD PAR SGRUB PA'I RIGS PA BSTAN PA STE
The whole point of these
verses is to explain to us
that we did have a past life. That's all.
All this argument about
Maitri's personality,
and this argument about
Maitri's state of mind,
and this argument about his sense powers,
it all ties back to, is there a past life?
Did you have a past life or not?
BYIS PA SKYES MA THAG PA'I
DBUGS 'BYUNG RNGUB SOGS RANG GI
RIGS 'DRA SNGA MA LAS BYUNG BA SGRUB NAS
This is now Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk talking.
Dharmakirti has demonstrated
that the living-ness,
the life, the breathing-ness of Maitri,
has come from some earlier
cause which is similar.
Life comes from life.
SGRUB NAS RIGS 'DRA SNGA
MA DE SKYE BA SNGA MA'I
DBUGS 'BYUNG RNGUB SOGS YIN PAR SHES
He wants you to understand
that the life energy
you see reflected in Maitri's breathing,
is an indication, like smoke
is an indication of fire,
that Maitri's living-breathing
is an indication
of a former living-breathing,
meaning past life.
That is Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk.
Fish picture.
Now, what does that have to do
with different color fishes?
I am getting there.
DA LTA'I SKYES MA THAG
PA'I DBANG SOGS RNAMS
'BYUNG BA 'BA' ZHIG LAS BYUNG NA
Now this is Geshe Yeshe
Wangchuk trying to make
Dharmakiti more clear to us.
Look, even if your eye powers:
your ears, eyes, ears, nose, tongue, skin,
even if they did come
from elements, chemicals,
let us say they came from chemicals.
Then if you have a sink
full of the same chemicals
why do you get different
kinds of beings popping up?
If the body came only from chemicals,
then if you put the same
chemicals in a pond,
you should get the same
creatures coming out
of those chemicals. But,
CHU GCIG GI NANG DU
'BU MGO DMAR LUS SER BA
But you see in some ponds
there are fish with red heads,
and yellow bodies. And
then you see other fish
with yellow heads and red bodies. Why?
If it is the same chemicals,
if it is the same chemicals,
why is there variation in the result?
SROG CHAGS 'GA' ZHIG
CHUNG LA 'GA' ZHIG CHE BA
Some of the creatures in the pond are big.
Some of the creatures
in the pond are small.
MI LA'ANG 'GA' ZHIG LUS
CHE LA 'GA' ZHIG CHUNG BA
Even among humans, you
get some with big bodies
and someone with small bodies.
RES 'GA' BLO GROS RNO LA RES 'GA' BRTUL PA
You see different people
popping out from the same
general chemical batch, from
the same general chemicals.
You get some people popping
up who are very smart,
and you get other people
popping up that are very stupid.
That indicates that it might
not be just the chemicals.
YANG PHRU GU 'GA' ZHIG
SHES RAB DANG BRTZE BA SOGS
CHE LA 'GA' ZHIG CHAGS
SOGS NYON MONG SHAS CHE BA
YOD PA SOGS MI 'THAD PAR 'GYUR TE
That must be incorrect
because also we see some kids,
young, young kids, some
are naturally gifted
with intelligence and
with love - BRTZE BA.
You have seen kids who come
up to you, you give them
a piece of candy and they
want to give back to you.
It always amazes me these kind of kids.
Wow, they did something I wouldn't do.
And then, CHAGS SOGS NYON
MONG, then you see other kids
who are very possessive of their toys,
you try to get them to share
a toy with somebody else
and they start getting angry and fighting.
So he says, this is an
indication that those kids minds,
personalities, sense powers are not just
coming from the chemicals in the womb.
If they were just coming from
the chemicals in the womb,
there should not be such
a variation of results
from the same batch of chemicals,
from the same pool of chemicals
you should get similar people.
RANG GI RIGS 'DRA SNGA
MA LA BLTOS MI DGOS PAR
'BYUNG BA TZAM LAS SKYE BA'I PHYIR
If they just grew from chemicals,
then their personality would not depend on
a past personality from a past life.
If they just grew from
chemicals, then since people
are growing from the
same kinds of chemicals,
they should be similar. They
should not be different.
YANG SROG CHAGS RNAMS 'BYUNG
BA 'BA' ZHIG LAS SKYES NA,
'BYUNG BA GCIG SROG CHAGS SU 'GYUR BA NA,
'BYUNG BA KUN SROG CHAGS SU 'GYUR BAR THAL
Then I will give you another argument.
Who is talking?
Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk.
He is trying to explain Dharmakirti to us.
He said, "Look, I finished the
root text, I taught you all
the words. Here is what
he is really saying."
SROG CHAGS RNAMS 'BYUNG
BA 'BA' ZHIG LAS SKYES NA
If living beings, if life was
created only from chemicals,
'BYUNG BA GCIG SROG CHAGS SU 'GYUR BA NA
then if one batch of
chemicals became a person,
'BYUNG BA KUN SROG CHAGS SU 'GYUR BAR THAL
then every time you have those chemicals,
there should be a Maitri.
Poof! Maitri comes. Why?
Well, there is nitrogen. There is oxygen.
There should be life wherever
those chemicals are present,
if it was only the chemicals
that created the life.
CHAGS SU 'GYUR BAR THAL,
'GYUR MI 'GYUR GYI RGYU RKYEN
GANG YANG MED PA'I PHYIR
Because what things are
and what things are not
follows from their causes
and their conditions.
RANG LUGS NI
What does it mean Tim?, RANG LUGS?
RANG LUGS
Come on, RANG LUGS.
Yes, Us guys.
Now Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk says,
"Hey, do I have you confused yet?"
- Yeah.
- Did you learn anything?
- Yeah, I think so.
- What did you learn?
- Maitri's personality did
not come from the chemicals
in Noor's womb.
- Okay, good. Well, okay, I understand.
- Where do you think his
personality came from?
Now, he says, "You want me to tell you?
You want to know my opinion where
Maitri's personality came from?"
YID BLO RTOG PA SNGA MA
'GA' ZHIG 'PHEN BYED KYI
RGYU BYED PA LAS DA LTAR
RNAM SMIN GYIS BSDUS PA'I
DBANG PO SOGS BYUNG LA
Maitri's personality and his sense powers
have come from karma, karmic
seeds, that were collected
in his mind, previously, in his past life.
Those are creating his
current personality.
'CHI KHA'I YID BLO RTOG PA
'GA' ZHIG GIS RGYU BYED PA LAS
And in particular, the
particular thoughts that
he was entertaining as he died,
'CHI KHA means in the moment of his death.
YID BLO RTOG PA 'GA'
ZHIG GIS RGYU BYED PA LAS
PHYI MA'I DBANG SOGS
KYANG 'BYUNG BAR 'GYUR BAS
The seeds of the mind at the
moment of this past life,
death, that had the NUS PA, had the power
to create his current personality.
Those seeds in his mind are what
created his current personality.
We are continuing.
By the way, do you have a
picture of me and a wall?
So now, Geshe Yeshe wants you to...
Hmm, the one before that, I hope.
Hmm, the picture before that,
unless I got. Hmm.
Why are you crying, Maitri? Is that you?
How about the one before that?
(laughing
- [Student] Still fish.
- Do you have a picture of a wall
and kids painting on a wall?
[Student] No.
I guess I left it out, okay.
Ah, do not worry about it, okay.
Let's see the commentary.
DE'I PHYIR, DBANG PO LNGA
RE RE LA GNOD NA YID BLO
'GYUR BAS KHYAB PA MED LA
If you think about it, you
can damage the sense power,
but that does not damage the mind.
You can have a happy person.
I met a lady like that in
Taiwan. She came to me,
very big business lady. Her
daughter brought me to her,
and she said that something happened.
First she told me how rich her mom is
and how successful her mom is.
And I am like, "Wow, that's cool."
Then she said, "Well, something happened."
And I said, "What?"
I do not know, I think she
was getting cosmetic surgery,
and they cut her optic
nerve, and she is blind.
They cut the nerve in
her eye and she is blind.
She got blind because she did not want to
have wrinkles or something.
Now she is blind, completely blind.
So you can hurt the sense power,
but that does not necessarily
make the person upset.
She was quite calm and
she was quite lucid,
and she was ready to keep working.
It is possible to damage the sense power.
It is possible to damage
the chemicals in the skin,
but not damage the
personality. It is possible.
KHYAB PA MED LA
YID BLO LA MYA NGAN DANG
'BYUNG PO SOGS KYIS 'GYUR NA
DBANG PO LA GNOD PAS KHYAB PA'I PHYIR
But if some kind of
influence of depression,
or you can say grief at
the loss of a loved one,
affects the mind strongly.
That does have an effect
on the chemicals of the
body. The person gets older.
The person gains weight or
things happen to depressed people.
All right.
So now you can show my chandelier, Pachi.
Generally, we have this feeling that...
and by the way, it took me a
long time to get this picture.
Understand this.
Generally, we say that this
is the past-life condition,
and this is the present-life condition.
The present-life condition is resting
on the past-life condition, right?
But it seems like to scientists
that Maitri's personality
is resting on chemicals
that were in his mom.
Maitri's mind is made from chemicals that
were in the soup inside his mom.
So it looks like his mind
is resting on the chemicals.
But with this chandelier,
it is not always the case
that the thing on top is what
is resting on the other thing.
The chandelier is resting on the ceiling.
The ceiling is holding up the chandelier.
It is not that the thing on the bottom
is always the support,
and the thing on top is always
what is being supported. Sometimes,
when you have a chandelier
hanging from the roof,
the roof is on top, but it
is holding up the chandelier.
So Maitri's personality did not come
from the chemicals in his mom's womb.
Maybe it is the opposite.
What's the opposite?
His personality created his mom's womb.
His personality created the
chemicals in his mom's womb.
Think about it that way.
DPER NA, YID LA 'JIGS SKRAG
SHUGS DRAG PA'I DUS NA,
LCE DBANG GIS RO ZHIM
PO MI MYONG BA BZHIN NO
For example, if you are drinking
a very good chocolate milkshake,
and then someone shows a gun in your face,
maybe you won't taste the chocolate.
Intense fear can affect the sense powers.
Therefore, the sense powers,
the chemicals are affected
by the mind and not the mind
coming from the chemicals.
It is very interesting.
'O NA, MIG DBANG NYAMS PA'I
STOBS KYIS MIG SHES KYI
YUL MI MTHONG BAR 'GYUR LA,
DES DBANG GIS YID LA MYA NGAN
BYUNG NAS YID BLO RTOG PA 'GYUR BA
MNGON SUM DU MTHONG BA'I PHYIR
The guy comes back with another argument.
We are almost done, hang in there.
"Yeah, yeah, that is right, but look,
when people go blind,
they get upset, right?
Most people get upset when they go blind."
"Yeah, most people get
upset when they go blind."
"Therefore, the skin is
controlling the personality."
You lose your physical skin eye,
you are going to be depressed and upset.
The guy says, "You can see that."
Therefore, there is a cause
and effect relationship
between chemicals and the mind.
People get upset when
they lose their eyes,
their eyesight. That is
chemicals affecting the mind.
Then he says... Who is that?
Geshe Yeshe Wangchuk,
being Dharmakirti, he says,
SKYON MED DE, DE LTAR 'GYUR BA YOD KYANG,
DBANG PO NYAMS PA'I STOBS KYIS
YID BLO 'GYUR BA MA YIN GYI,
MIG DBANG NYAMS PA DES RKYEN BYAS NAS
YID LA MYA NGAN GZHAN ZHIG
Look, I agree, there are cases,
where people lose their
eyesight and they get upset.
But that is not the change in the
mental state was not caused
by the change in the eye.
MIG DBANG NYAMS PA DES RKYEN BYAS NAS
The loss of the eye was only a factor,
RKYEN, not the main cause.
YID LA MYA NGAN GZHAN ZHIG
BYUNG MYA NGAN DE JE RGYAS
SU SONG BAS YID BLO YANG
'GYUR BA YIN PA'I PHYIR,
It is not that, by the way,
without sustaining more damage
to your eye, you can also
get more and more upset.
So that the damage to the eye
contributes to the depression,
but it is not that as
you get more depressed,
your eye got more damaged.
Got it?
All right. Morover,
MIG DBANG NYAMS PA TZAM
GYIS YID BLO RTOG PA
'GYUR BA MA YIN TE
It is not also the case that every time
they lose their eyes, people get upset.
BDAG NYID CHEN PO 'GA' ZHIG
GIS MIG SBYIN PA BTANG YANG
YID LA BDE BA 'BYUNG BA YOD PA'I PHYIR
Some BDAG NYID CHEN POs.
What does that mean?
Some Mahatmas, some great people,
when they give away their
eyes, they get more...
[Student] Happy.
[GMR] Happy (laughing.
Somebody says, "Can you give me your eye?
Would you give me one of your kidneys?"
And they are like, "Sure,
thanks for asking."
Yeah, take my kidney.
And they feel happier.
Therefore, it is not that a
reduction in the cell count,
by cutting a kidney,
will make a corresponding
reduction in the happiness level.
You cut out one kidney,
you are not half as happy.
Some people cut out and
give their kidney away,
and they get twice as happy. Therefore,
it is not the cells that
create the personality.
DE LTAR NA, YID BLO RTOG PA DE, RANG 'BRAS
DBANG SOGS KYI LDOG BYED KYI
RGYU KHYAD PAR CAN YIN GYI
Therefore, it is the state of mind
that has power over the
condition of the cells.
DBANG PO LA SOGS PA RNAMS
RANG 'BRAS YID BLO RTOG PA
LDOG BYED KYI RGYU KHYAD PAR CAN MA YIN NO
It is not the case that
damage to the cells
has to have a corresponding
effect in the mind.
DON BSDUS NA
That is going to give you guys
some hope because it means,
let me summarize for
you guys DON BSDUS NA.
SKYES MA THAG PA'I RIG PA CHOS CAN
Let´s take the mental state of Maitri,
just after he was born.
RIG PA SNGA MA SNGON DU SONG STE
That is smoke that
indicates a fire before.
Meaning, if Maitri has a state of mind,
which is friendly now, he
must have had a state of mind
before he went into his mom.
RIG PA YIN PA'I PHYIR, DPER
NA, DA LTA'I RIG PA BZHIN
ZHES PA SKYE BA SNGA MA SGRUB PA DANG
The same thing is going to
happen with your personality
right now. Your personality
as you listen to this long argument,
is going to help make your personality
when you finish this video.
Your current personality,
as you listen to this long
argument, is going to create
how you feel after this video.
But the way you felt during
the video is proof that
you were feeling some way
before the video. Got it?
The fact that you have a mind
now is going to be reflected
in the mind you have after
the video. But the fact that
you have a mind during the video
shows that you had in
mind before the video.
THA MAL PA'I 'CHI KHA'I RIG
PA CHOS CAN, RIG PA PHYI MA
MTSAMS SBYOR TE, CHAGS BCAS
KYI RIG PA YIN PA'I PHYIR,
Then he says, look, the fact
that, by the way, he says,
the fact that your
awareness in your past life
could trigger an awareness in this life,
if both awarenesses are in sansara,
the wheel of life and suffering,
it says something not only about
your previous state of mind
but about the content of
your previous state of mind.
Your previous state of mind
must have been screwed up
in some way that caused
it to be born in a place
where it had to die again.
TSIG LA 'KHRID NA, RIG PA
SNGA MA CHOS CAN, RIG PA
SNGA MA SNGON DU SONG BAR
THAL, RIG PA YIN PA'I PHYIR,
RIG PA PHYI MA CHOS CAN, RIG
PA PHYI MA MTSAMS SBYOR BAR
THAL, CHAGS BCAS KYI RIG PA
YIN PA'I PHYIR, RTAGS KHYAB KUN
KHAS,'DOD MI NUS TE, RANG
RANG DANG GCIG YIN PA'I PHYIR
I am going to skip that...
Do you want to skip it or...
you do not want to skip it?
You do not want to skip it.
He says, "Look, if you want to
get confused with the words?
You want me to mess
you up with the words?"
"Yeah, mess me up with the words."
Okay, here we go.
TSIG LA 'KHRID NA means you want me to,
do you want me to tie
you up with the words,
until you do not know what I am saying?
- Yeah, okay, let us do it.
'KHRID means to embrace
somebody which is kind of funny.
Do you want me to give
you a verbal hug so hard
that you can not remember
what I am talking about?
RIG PA SNGA MA CHOS CAN
Let's take Maitri's mind in his past life.
RIG PA SNGA MA SNGON DU SONG BAR THAL
It must have been in the past
RIG PA YIN PA'I PHYIR
because he has a mind
RIG PA PHYI MA CHOS CAN
Let´s take Maitri's thoughts
when he is 20 years old.
RIG PA PHYI MA MTSAMS SBYOR BAR THAL
It must give birth to thoughts
when he is 40 years old. Why?
CHAGS BCAS KYI RIG PA YIN PA'I PHYIR
Because it is not the kind
of personality that is going
to get him out of that
sansara if it has desire,
if it has attachment to self existence.
'DOD MI NUS TE, RANG RANG
DANG GCIG YIN PA'I PHYIR,
DE DAG NI, SLOB DPON KA
MA LA SH'I LAS, SKYE BA
SNGA PHYI SGRUB PA DANG 'DRA BA YIN TE
This is very similar to the
way in which Kamalashila
proves past and future life.
That is all, I think we can stop it there.
What now, Geshe-la, what just happened?
Do not ask me, look at the video.
Look at the video five times.
Thank God for videos. Look
at the video five times.
Yeah, but why did we just go through that?
I thought we were doing Lam Rim.
No, you do not understand.
He just proved you had a past life.
Now what does it have
to do with the Lam Rim?
If you had a past life,
then, you had a past life...
[Student] You had as a mother.
- Mom
If I can prove to you that
you were alive five minutes
before you were born.
If I can prove to you
that you were alive five
minutes before you were born,
then I have proved that
every living being around you
has been your mother.
Got it?
I will say it again. If I can prove that
you were alive five minutes
before you were born,
that before you came into your mom.
If I can prove that your mind
was working at the moment.
Then I have proved that every living being
around you is your mother.
And if you agree that you were alive,
and that's what gave
life to you in your mom,
then that in itself
proves that every person
you ever met in your
life has been your mom.
We'll tie it up in the next show.
We'll tie it up in the next class.
But do not forget what I said.
If you were alive five minutes
before your life in this mom,
and if your life in this mom
did not come from
chemicals, dead chemicals,
then every being, every person
you ever met in your life
has been your mom.
Now we have to go through
that, but we will.
All right. See you in the next class. Yay!